Guide to the Instructors' Association Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Instructors' Association records
1919-1947
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
5065
Instructors' Association (University of Washington)
ca. 1.04 cubic ft
The Instructors’ Association was a professional organization founded by University of Washington faculty on October 22, 1919 in order to investigate major issues facing faculty and advocate for their needs to the university administration. This collection spans the years 1919-1947 and contains correspondence, meeting minutes, reports, resolutions, financial records, and other textual material created and/or kept by the association.
Recognizing the need for an organization to investigate issues facing University of Washington faculty, the Instructors’ Association was founded by faculty with the support of President Henry Suzzallo at a meeting on October 22, 1919. The association served as a liaison between faculty, including members of the American Federation of Teachers Union, Local No. 401, and university administration. A Board of Directors of seven annually elected individuals governed the organization and several standing committees were created to research specific issues. Through these investigations, often administered through questionnaires distributed to university faculty, the association would compile reports and make recommendations to the administration based on the results. Major issues explored by the Instructors’ Association include promotions and faculty salaries; faculty’s role in appointment of university presidents; retirement and annuity; sabbatical leave; university personnel policies, including a policy that prohibited married faculty members to both teach at the university; teaching load; cost of living; taxes; state and local funding; university budget and expenditures; tenure; and healthcare and insurance. Although the records stop at year 1947, it is currently unknown when the Instructors' Association officially disbanded.
Organized into 3 accessions.
Accession No. 5065-001, Instructors' Association records, 1919-1946
Accession No. 5065-002, Instructors' Association records, 1919-1947
Accession No. 5065-003, Instructors' Association report, 1938
Correspondence, reports, resolutions, meeting notices and minutes, published material, organizational charts, university policies.
Open to all users.
Boettiger, John,$d1900-1950; Harris, Joseph Pratt,$d1896-1985; James, Florence Bean,$d1892-1988; Johnson, Claudius O.$q(Claudius Osborne),$d1894-1976; Kerr, Clark,$d1911-2003; Kizer, Benjamin H.$q(Benjamin Hamilton),$d1878-1978; Miller, Lea P.; Schweppe, Alfred John,$d1895-1988; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); American Federation of Teachers.$bLocal 401 (Seattle, Wash.).; Instructors' Association (University of Washington)$vArchives; University of Washington.$bPresident.
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Colleges and Universities
- Instructors' Association records, 1919-1946; 5065-001; .21 cu.ft.
  Materials are arranged in two folders based on the original order they were found in during reprocessing.
  This accession spans the years 1919-1946 and contains correspondence between Instructors’ Association board members, faculty, and university administration; reports; resolutions; meeting notices and minutes; and published material. Subjects discussed include salary increases and promotion, teaching load, role of faculty in appointment of university presidents, retirement annuity, faculty dismissal, sabbatical leave, disability, and insurance. Particular items of note include a news clipping and meeting notice from October 1919 regarding the first meeting held by faculty that established the association as well as a small bound report titled, "The Salary Situation at the University of Washington: A Report to the Board of Regents by the Association of Instructors."
  Open to all users.
  President's Office, 1968-04-16
  - Correspondence, Meeting Minutes, Resolutions, and Reports, 1919-1926 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Correspondence, Meeting Minutes, Resolutions, and Reports, 1928-1946 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Instructors' Association records, 1919-1947; 5065-002; .83 cu.ft.
  Materials within this accession are arranged into the following series:
  Series I: Organization
  Series II: Correspondence
  Series III: Reports
  Series IV: Meeting Notices and Minutes
  Series V: Financial Records
  Series VI: Subject Files
  This accession spans the years 1919-1947 and contains organizational charts; university policies; correspondence between members of the association and university presidents, faculty members, the American Federation of Teachers Local No. 401, and government officials; official reports of the Instructors’ Association Board, official recommendations made by the association to the university administration on specific issues, and other reports compiled by association members; association meeting notices and minutes; financial reports, including university receipts and expenditures and other materials related to university finances; and subject files compiled by the association on various topics. Subject matter consists of assorted issues affecting University of Washington faculty, including retirement and annuity, salary, legislative initiatives, funding, instructor workload, university policies, tenure, sabbatical leave, medical care and insurance, emeritus faculty, relationship between the university administration and Instructor’s Association, and faculty leave of absence and dismissal cases.
  Also included is a large bound record book of the Instructors’ Association Board containing handwritten and typed meeting minutes, correspondence, news clippings, and reports. Some of these materials are likely duplicated within other series of this accession.
  Unknown
  - ORGANIZATION, 1929-1946; SERIES I (Box-folder 1/1-1/3)
    - Member Group Insurance at University of Washington, 1929 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Administrative and Legal Organization of Faculty, Undated, 1938 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - University of Washington Faculty and Staff Annual Salaries, c. 1934-1946 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - CORRESPONDENCE, 1925-1946; SERIES II (Box-folder 1/4-1/15)
    - Assorted Correspondence, 1934-1939 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Assorted Interdepartmental Correspondence, 1927-1942 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Assorted Intradepartmental Correspondence, Undated, 1925-1946 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - American Federation of Teachers, Local No. 401, 1936-1938 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - State Legislation, 1934-1938 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - State Teachers Retirement Fund, 1926 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Faculty Salary Adjustments, 1934 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Survey of Tenure at Other Universities, 1944 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Faculty Health Care and Insurance, 1935-1938, 1946 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Instructors' Association Fund, 1942 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Community Fund, 1938-1940 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - Faculty Dismissal Policies and Investigations, 1934-1938 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - REPORTS, 1919-1946; SERIES III (Box-folder 1/16-1/25)
    - American Association of University Professors' Preliminary Report on Faculty Salaries, 1946 May (Box-folder 1/16)
    - "Initiative 153: Effect Upon the Powers of the Board of Regents" [On Sale of Public Land], c. 1941 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - Instructors' Association Board Reports, 1937-1942 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - Faculty Personnel Policies, 1940 May (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Instructors' Association Reports, 1919, 1927 (Box-folder 1/20)
    - Instructors' Association Reports, 1933-1934 (Box-folder 1/21)
    - Instructors' Association Reports, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 1/22)
    - Instructors' Association Reports, Undated (Box-folder 1/23)
    - Instructors' Association Recommendations, c. 1933-1939 (Box-folder 1/24)
    - Tenure Practices in Other State Universities, c. 1945 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - MEETING NOTICES AND MINUTES, 1922-1937; SERIES IV (Box-folder 1/26-1/28, 2/13)
    - Meeting Notices, 1922-1925 (Box-folder 1/26)
    - Meeting Notices, 1926 (Box-folder 1/27)
    - Meeting Notices, Undated, 1937 (Box-folder 1/28)
    - Instructors' Association Board Record Book, 1929-1947 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - FINANCIAL RECORDS, 1926-1946; SERIES V (Box-folder 1/29-1/30, 2/1-2/3)
    - Treasurer's Record Book, 1942-1946 (Box-folder 1/29)
    - Board Summary of University Income and Expenditures, c. 1937 (Box-folder 1/30)
    - Receipts and Expenditure Reports, 1929-1939 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Statistical Graphs on State University Enrollment, Teaching, and Financial Data, c. 1934 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Life Insurance Credit Memorandums and Termination Reports, 1926-1929 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - SUBJECT FILES, 1922-1939; SERIES VI (Box-folder 2/4-2/12)
    - Florence B. James Leave of Absence and Tenure Case, 1936-1939 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Medical Care and Insurance, c. 1934-1938 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Lea Puymbroeck Miller Dismissal Case, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Questionnaires, c. 1938-1939 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Faculty Retirement and Annuity, c. 1937-1938 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - University of Washington Rules and Regulations, c. 1937-1938 (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Legislative Initiatives, 1934-1939 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - Sabbatical Leave Studies, c. 1938-1939 (Box-folder 2/11)
    - Legislative Initiatives and State Taxes, c. 1922-1938 (Box-folder 2/12)
- Instructors' Association report, 1938; 5065-003; 1 vertical file
  This accession contains a single printed report of the Instructors’ Association Board published on April 25, 1938. The report contains a discussion by the Insurance Committee on retirement annuity and health and accident insurance as well as the University of Washington’s recommended plan for faculty retirement.
  Robert Hennes, 1987-05-01
  - Report of the Board, 1938 (Box-folder VF1916)